<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2. Securing Containers on Kubernetes Security Training</title><link>/docs/container-basics/02-security/</link><description>Recent content in 2. Securing Containers on Kubernetes Security Training</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="/docs/container-basics/02-security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2.1 SSDLC</title><link>/docs/container-basics/02-security/02/_ssdlc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/container-basics/02-security/02/_ssdlc/</guid><description>Secure Software Development Lifecycle Docker security covers the entire lifecycle of containers, including their runtime, build process, and orchestration. Key security areas include base images, Dockerfiles, container runtimes, and securing the Docker daemon. Additionally, it&amp;rsquo;s important to configure container isolation, manage user privileges effectively, and follow security best practices when orchestrating containers at scale.
To ensure we fully understand and manage our workload, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to focus on our Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC).</description></item><item><title>2.2 Privileges</title><link>/docs/container-basics/02-security/02/_privileges/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/container-basics/02-security/02/_privileges/</guid><description>Before exploring different options to minimize container privileges, it&amp;rsquo;s important to address a fundamental yet frequently overlooked practice: keeping your software up to date. Regular updates are crucial for protecting against known container escape vulnerabilities, such as Leaky Vessels , which often allow attackers to gain root access to the host. This means both the host system and Docker itself must be consistently updated, including the host kernel and Docker Engine.</description></item></channel></rss>